<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A just account of truth and peace, given-in by brethren, lovers of and fellow-helpers to both, wherefore they must open their matters to the view of the world, speaking them, in their respective places, as upon the house-tops, which else had been spoken in darknesse privately, and as in the eare.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E868_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207686</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866724</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866724</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96895)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E868[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A just account of truth and peace, given-in by brethren, lovers of and fellow-helpers to both, wherefore they must open their matters to the view of the world, speaking them, in their respective places, as upon the house-tops, which else had been spoken in darknesse privately, and as in the eare.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed according to order for Henry Cripps, in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>To the reader signed: Hezekiah Woodvvard.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By Hezekiah Woodward".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Separatists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119008:1"/>
            <p>A juſt Account Upon the Account of truth and peace, given-in by Brethren, lovers of and fellow-helpers to both, wherefore they muſt open their matters to the view of the world, <hi>ſpeaking them, in their reſpective places, as upon the houſe-tops,</hi> which elſe had been ſpoken in <hi>darkneſſe</hi> private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and as <hi>in the eare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They take away the righteouſneſſe of the righteous from them.</hi> Iſa. 5. 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every day they wreſt my words,</hi> Pſal. 56. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which they that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt, as they alſo doe other Scriptures,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee are made manifest unto God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed according to Order for <hi>Henry Cripps,</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119008:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119008:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE are</hi> angariated <hi>(wee make bold with that</hi> Perſian <hi>word, our</hi> Engliſh <hi>being ſo ſhort in our ſeeming to expreſſe the enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that lyeth upon us</hi>) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, <hi>as one was to beare the Croſſe, or as a tired horſe to goe his Stage: ſo we to put-forth our matters, as we intend to doe one after another, for others to judge betwixt us and a Miniſter of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Hs <hi>perſwaſion in</hi> Reference to the Diſcipline of Gods Houſe, free Admiſſion of all to all Church-Communions; <hi>It is poſſible, and but after the manner of men, and more ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with ſuch as we are, to judge amiſſe of our own performances, too partially and fatherlike (for</hi> libri quaſi liberi, <hi>books are like children) we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-look their faults, or we deal too tenderly with them, as others may too raſhly and rigedly. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as things now ſtand, the world must judge betwixt us, or as many of them as are fitted with patience to ſit out the hearing of ſo meane matters,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119008:3"/> 
               <hi>as they are acted by us, as mean as the meaneſt, and may be preſented to their eye and eare in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and reſpective places; Meane we ſay as acted by us, but in their relation to the</hi> houſe of <hi>God, the</hi> Church of the living God, <hi>the management of matters by the Stewards there, they may appear to be matters high and Glorious, just according to the manner they are mannaged, if after the due order, then high and glorious, if otherwiſe, then low and inglorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now be not diſcouraged, Reader at our mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, though ſo meane wee are as thou canſt think us. We would gladly ſuppoſe thee a bleſſed man; the bent of whoſe Spirit is ſuch, that he cannot ſtirre or make the leaſt motion againſt the Truth. And then it is a bleſſed comfort to this bleſſed man (to thee, if thou be hee) that though wee ſhould put forth our ſtrength, not ingorantly onely but wickedly (which through grace is as far from us, as wee would have that to be, which is an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to us) againſt the truth, yet we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prevail againſt it, which undoubtedly will be the</hi> great Conquerour at laſt, <hi>&amp; is gaining every day</hi> luſter and Glory <hi>by our most inglorious act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt it. Queſtionleſs, it is</hi> ventilated <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed and purged by the</hi> blaſtings <hi>of men of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119008:3"/> 
               <hi>minds upon it; ſurely it is cleared from the droſs (which would cleave to it) paſſing through ſo many heated hands and fiery mouths, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> fining pots, <hi>though intended by man utterly to extinguiſh and conſume it: oh the glorious advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages truth hath gained all along theſe</hi> feirce <hi>and</hi> perilous times, <hi>while errour</hi> ſate in ſtate, <hi>or as we may ſay in its</hi> Throne, <hi>like to be, as might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by ſome,</hi> a perpetuall Dictator <hi>againſt it;</hi> It is the Lords doing, is it not marvelous in your eyes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to ſtay thee no longer, we come to our caſe, which, in brief, is this; we were deſired (ſo wee would rather ſay than charged or commanded, wee ſhould be judged elſe to walke by a fancy in the matters of our Lord) by a Miniſter of the ſame perſwaſion with a world (but</hi> argumentum peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum turba, <hi>commonly the moſt are worſt) of Miniſters, to give our reaſons for our diſſent from him in point of free</hi> admiſſion of all to all Church Communions upon account of their infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; <hi>As alſo to the</hi> declaring againſt the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the day <hi>wee will call, becauſe we would be underſtood,</hi> Chriſtmas Day, <hi>in reference alſo to</hi> forms of prayer, <hi>and in ſpeciall to the</hi> Lords prayer; <hi>and foure</hi> Queries <hi>thereupon; Theſe foure</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119008:4"/> 
               <hi>Treatiſes, (for ſo wee have digeſted them) with three Epiſtles, together with an introduction hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth by way of preface, the way of Chriſt with His people, and their walke with Him, by the guidance of his good Spirit in the directions of His Word, theſe, wee were ſaying, wee ſent to the ſaid Miniſter one after another, as wee could take a tranſcript of the ſame; ſome two months after he returned us the Epiſtles, Preface, and firſt Treatiſe of</hi> Baptiſme, <hi>with ſome exceptions againſt ſome expreſſions or paſſages in all three; whereunto we thought our ſelves bound, upon the account of truth, to make ſome Reply, whereof you may be judge, if pleaſe you; For truely our</hi> Humours, <hi>or our</hi> principles, <hi>the one or both are ſo contrary, that though we are bound to judge our ſelves, yet neither muſt wee nor will wee be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in our matters, though indeed we think them to be right, and well agreeing with the Word of God, if that ſaid Miniſter fixed in Mr</hi> H<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 
               <hi>way, and firme to his perſwaſion, be in an errour as to theſe matters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quickly after the receite of this our Reply to his exceptions, as aforeſaid, he returned, together with that Reply, the three other Treatiſes (all he had or would receive from us, whereas there were</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119008:4"/> 
               <hi>three more in our hands, in a readineſſe for him) with ſo much heate as might argue his ſpirit ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſcompoſed. Notwithſtanding though ſome might think here was ſome offence given in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning our Papers, wee expected no more than wee doe the returne of our waters where they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ebb nor flow, yet truely there was no offence taken, they were received, and little regarded by us, having, as wee ſaid, a tranſcript of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some three weekes after, the ſaid Miniſter ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one amongst us whether wee had looked into our papers he had returned to us? anſwer was made, no; he bad us look into our Treatiſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (wherein our endeavour and care was to be ſtudiouſly curious) and there wee ſhould ſee what his ſon had written. Wee did, as hee deſired, and quickly found his ſons handy work for ſome leaves together, as pleaſed him, or him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him,</hi> falſe gloſſes, unjuſt conſtructions, the blackeſt lines <hi>did that young man draw-over ours in many places; and, at length, down-right blaſphemy charged he upon us. Whereat we were ſtartled a little at preſent, not becauſe the ſon of that Minister charged us ſo deeply; for he was, as ſome ſay, very youthfull till of late, when the</hi> hands of the Presbytery <hi>were laid upon him;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119008:5"/> 
               <hi>what change was wrought upon him at that time, or ſince that day, they ſhould know, who live neere him, heare his Doctrines, and ſee his practiſe; But youthfull he was, as is ſaid after the manner of young folk; and then as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaid, all in him, or don by him was childiſh while he was a child: ſo happely in the next ſtep of our life which is youth, he that is a youth thinks as a youth, ſpeaks as a youth, acts as a youth, all in him, or don by him is youthfull, that is,</hi> ſubject to miſcarriages and miſtakes, <hi>therefore wee, as wee were ſaying, regarded little what the ſon ſaid</hi> ſpeaking of his own, <hi>nor can wee think it ſtrange, that a youth ſhould act like a youth</hi> (every age of our life ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſomething peculiar to its ſelf.) <hi>But this we think ſtrange, That the ſon charged our book ſo in the preſence of his father, and where two learned and pious Divines, as is meete for us to judge, were preſent at the ſame time, whoſe names wee ſhall mention in the enſuing papers.</hi> You <hi>have heard our caſe, wee will detaine thee no longer, when wee have added this, That having offered our matters ſucceſleſly to that Miniſter, returning them with ſuch a</hi>—caſtigation <hi>(as the like, wee think, hath not been heard or read) though wee were charged by him to give him our perſwaſion,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119008:5"/> 
               <hi>and the reaſon thereof, in reference to the matters aforeſaid, we find our ſelves</hi> conſtrained <hi>to make our matters publick; which we doe the more cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, being confident of this thing, That there is nothing here, or in that, which may follow after, which is againſt</hi> piety <hi>or</hi> charity; <hi>for wee had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our bones ſhould be ſcattered like chips about the hewing-place, than that our pen (which hath the advantage of the tongue, more hearers) ſhould as others doe in this ſcribling age ſcatter errour and wickedneſſe among the people, as the Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on its poyſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee truſt the Good Hand of Him (our onely</hi> leane-to, and that leads into all truth) <hi>ſo far, as that wee hope you ſhall find</hi> Truth <hi>all along, and mannaged in our meaſure, as becometh</hi> ſons of truth, <hi>and fellow-helpers of the ſame; This Good Spirit direct your heart to the love of Christ, which onely is conſtraining to love Truth and peace; and to keepe both as thou keepeſt the apple of thine eye, or thy chiefeſt Treaſure.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In the Name and by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">10. 5. 55.</note> of their Paſtour, HEZEKIAH WOODVVARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:119008:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119008:6"/>
            <head>SECT 1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue is the Proverb, Sir, <hi>The beginning of ſtrife, is, as when one lets-out water,</hi> ſtirred quickly, not ſo quickly ſtinted; ſo like water it is of a ſpreading nature; or as like unto fire, which may breake-forth from a <hi>bramble</hi> and devour a <hi>Cedar.</hi> There is no ſuch feare of our fire, as you are pleaſed to call it, though being now let-out, it may ſpread like water; and ſo it ſhall doe, if wee can help the ſpreading of it, That it may appeare, how and where it began, with the riſe and originall of it, how it was raiſed, yea forced: From whence you may learne and <hi>ſtudie to be quiet, and meddle in your own matters,</hi> walking peaceably in your owne way, ſo pleaſing in your owne eyes; And not meddle with others in theirs, fully reſolved from the word of God to be the <hi>way of Truth and of Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely it had been no contemptible point of your wiſdome, and might have argued good Diſcretion, <hi>"To have left this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, before it was meddled with,</hi> which to render according to th'originall, you may better skill of than we. Onely this we would ſay as to the ſtirring in this ſtrife againe, That wee did not <hi>uſe lightneſſe, nor did wee purpoſe according to the fleſh,</hi> never more to meddle therein, for ſo we ſaid to you in our laſt, intending it the laſt you ſhould ever have from us, either by Letter, word, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, in reference to thoſe matters under Debate. For as wee ſaid then, "<hi>To what end?</hi> we had given our opinion as you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us, and there might have been an end. <q rend="margQuotes">Wee have experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this Truth, "<hi>That Errour is as binding upon the Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>as ſtrongly embraced by the affections as Truth is,</hi> binding of us, and Embraced by us, not in the name of an Errour, but of Truth; And men are therefore wedded to and in love with their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119008:7"/> owne Conceptions, becauſe (how monſtrous and hard-favoured ſoever in themſelves, yet) nothing is more beautifull in their eye, than they. "No man, ſaith the Apoſtle, ever hated his owne fleſh, but loveth and cheriſheth it:</q> The fleſh of our minds (ſuch are all falſe principles and poſitions) is more loved and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by us than the fleſh of our Bodyes. A light intimation (we proceed in his words upon <hi>Iob</hi> 22 verſe) or onely the appearance of a probability, will amount to a proof againſt either perſons <hi rend="margQuotes">or doctrines, which we like not; But the cleareſt Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will hardly raiſe a jealouſie againſt what we like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have given, Sir, we feare, a very ſad experience of this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, For how ſtubborne and unmoved are you from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> his errour in point of admiſſion of all (filthineſſe all over, and wallowing therein as ſwine in the mire, admitted notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) to all Church-Communions, the Lords Supper and all, Though the ſtrongeſt winds of Truth have breathed, yea blowne hard upon it.</p>
            <p>That you might not be willingly ignorant of this very thing, and withall to ſhew our deare reſpects unto you, wee told you, That foure Worthies of the Lord had Encountred with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> about the premiſes, and with as much eaſe, (to phraſe it as one doth) and with like ſucceſſe, as the fire doth the dried ſtubble; and yet he ſtubbornely holds to it, for ought we know, we know you doe, remaining in the ſame minde with him, that foreforne man (Generally we think deceived by the Godly all over the Land) as a Mountaine unmoved to this very houre. Wee know not which is worſe, but leave it to you to judge, "<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſetledneſſe in the Truth, and an Eaſineſſe to let it goe; or tenaciouſneſſe in an error, and an hardneſſe to let it goe. Nor doe we know well, which is worſe, a readineſſe to take up hard thoughts of our Brethren, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readineſſe to lay them downe;</hi> onely this we know, Were the lawes of Zeale for God obſerved, and of Love to man, you could not, as we thinke, "<hi>Deſpiſe the day of ſmall things,</hi> or rhe leaſt breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or fainteſt endeavours of any, how meane and weake ſoever (as babes in Chriſt uſe to be) enquiring after Truth, and that old, but now forſaken way of holineſſe; <hi>Asking the way to Zion, with their faces thetherward, ſaying, Come</hi>—&amp;c. <hi>Ier:</hi> 50. 5. And did you obſerve the Law of Charity to man, it would cauſe you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119008:7"/> to examine every ground of ſuſpicion againſt a Brother twice, before you did indeed ſuſpect him once: And you would rejoyce in any appearance of his innocence, whereby you might diſcharge your owne Spirit of all ſuſpicions concerning him. Theſe words, we hope, will not be as wind with you, though ours are and have been to this time Therefore, as we ſaid, we had ſorborne to ſpeak, nay we doe forbeare to ſpeake more unto you, unleſſe you hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to light on it, but forbeare to ſpeake we may not, we cannot, for thus it was as you very well know.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>SECT. II.</head>
            <p>YOu would needs point us to ſomething, your <hi>Son</hi> had written (for that Title better becomes us, though <hi>Childe</hi> better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits him) in our <hi>Treatiſe of prayer,</hi> as if you would have us take ſpeciall notice thereof, which indeed we have done, for ſo a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence caſt it, elſe we had not looked into it, having a Tranſcript of the ſame: but upon your motion, you telling us, where we ſhould find your ſon's hand, we quickly turned to it, and found as you ſaid, taking, as you willed-us ſpeciall notice thereof, Not becauſe your Son did write it, but becauſe you his Father ſuffered him ſo to doe, againſt th'old and knowne rule of Civility, as Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars would ſay, and of all good manners too; which you could not have ſuffered to be done (it is our perſwaſion) had you not had a vile account of our <hi>Paſtour,</hi> who was chiefe, if not alone in that worke: See! when a father contemneth a man (but what is the Contempt of a man, ſuppoſe it little or much? or how ſmall a thing is it with him to be accounted vile in another's eyes, who is, we hope, yet more vile in his owne? but) ſee, when a Father vilifieth a man, his Son <hi>(indulget ſibi latius)</hi> will vilifie him much more, and venture (ſo arrogant and bold youth is) to paſſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in thoſe matters, which he underſtandeth not ſo well now, as he, whom your Son ſo raſhly judgeth and dealeth ſo—as ſome would ſay withall, as to ſay, "<hi>He blaſphemeth,</hi> underſtood them before your Son was borne. But all this argueth your high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, That the Truth in thoſe points, to which our Debate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, is on your ſide. Be it ſo, though it be but your Confidence, the ſame with Mr <hi>H:</hi> yet to charge us, our Paſtour ſpecially ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119008:8"/> deeply for maintaining the Contrary; You giving a Charge to ſpeake our minds, and to make them legible in thoſe matters, is, as ſome have ſaid, but one peg at the moſt below impudence. And this is all we will ſay in this place, telling you what ſome ſay, and haply they would adde, though we forbeare. Onely we would leave you, after you ſhall have heard more, to paſſe ſentence on your ſelfe and your ſon for this behaviour. We will turne aſide from this a little, and returne to it at the laſt, ſo ſoone as we have taken-in three or foure things firſt, for ſo you have thought fitt, we had almoſt ſaid to face us, yea to force us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>SECT. III.</head>
            <p>WEE, as we were ſaying, fully intended to ceaſe the ſtrife, ſith it hath proved ſuch a thing, and to leave the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with Him, the Judge of all the world, and "know's the hearts of all men; who will, we hope, ſhew you and us in His owne beſt time; Who hath ſpoken much, and in deſire and Endeavour as much to purpoſe; who hath ſaid little in Compariſon, and yet leſſe to the matters under hand. And yet ſhould you be able to putt off all with that old putt-off (whereto ſome thing will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied anon after) <hi>multa dicit, nihil probat,</hi> The man ſpeaks much, and proves nothing, or nothing concludingly, and ſo folly is with us, (for your charge of Blaſphemie, yours, which you ſuffered to be charged, is too high) why yet, ſuppoſing all that, The errour is on our ſide, and Truth on yours (which were ſtrange, if not impoſſible, you ſideing with M <hi>Hs:</hi> and driving-on with him in the ſame way) Notwithſtanding, we faint not in our minds, For our matters are humbly committed to th'onely wiſe God, Who is able, and we are Confident He will, make emprovements out of folly (on whoſe ſide ſoever it be) and give advantage to His Truth, by the <hi>breaking-out of Errour, and falſity; As it is one of the higheſt acts of Grace,</hi> (ſo one of us have read) <hi>in man, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der good for evill: ſo is it one of the higheſt acts of power to draw good out of evill.</hi> Upon this God All ſufficient we waite. He alwayes hitherto <hi>hath extracted the cleane thing of His Glory</hi> (as one ſaith upon <hi>Daniel) out of the filthineſſe of Man's ſin;</hi> our Confidence is, He will doe ſo now, He brought light out of Darkneſſe at the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119008:8"/> firſt, "<hi>marveilous in our eyes,</hi> not "hard and "difficult to Him; By His Grace wee will Truſt Him, He will make a bleſſed, yea a Glorious method of theſe Curſed Confuſions, cauſed by Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> in His houſe; and, notwithſtanding all is ſaid againſt it by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly men, maintained by you. 2. And Sir, That we may tell you our boaſtings in our God, our hope being ſet on Him, This good is come of it already; which wee will call a good bleſſing, wee meane of this Debate, in Reference to "<hi>free Admiſſion of all to all Church-Communions, upon account of their Infant Baptiſme onely, without making ſo much as a profeſſion of their Faith and repentance,</hi> your Brothers conceit: Wee were ſaying, This good is come of it, That we are aboundantly ſatisfied as to the Negative, hearing it as clearely made out unto us from the word of God, as if it had been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Sun-beames: And by the helpe of His Grace, we ſhall hold unto it, while life is held within us, being the more confirmed, if more can be, and our foote more eſtabliſhed in that way, by that little or nothing you have ſaid againſt it, (for you have ſaid all for Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> and not a word for the way of Holineſſe) ſo as neither your ſelfe, nor all the men of your way and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though ſo numerous that they fill the Countries (no good argument of their goodneſſe, or the ſtraightneſſe of their way) can be able to draw us aſide from this way God hath pointed us to, leadeth us in, and you called us ſorth to maintaine, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſhockes againſt it, ſcornings and blaſtings upon it, and upon us for the way's-ſake; not more able, we were ſaying, to draw us from it, than ye are able to remove a mountaine from it's roots, or ſtay the Sunne in it's Courſe, or blow it out with a paire of bellowes. So ſtrong is Truth, and ſo ſtrong are all they that by the good Hand of their God are ſtabliſhed therein.</p>
            <p>Wee adde this more, This Truth, you accounting it an Errour, and of the lateſt Date, called us forth to maintaine, how weakly ſoever maintained by us, as you ſay, and we doe not gaine-ſay, ſhall be glorious notwithſtanding (for it needs not our patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage) in the eyes of the Lord, and of His people, when your looſe and more than airy Tenet againſt it, The ſame with Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> ſhall be for an hiſſing unto both; To uſe worthy Mr <hi>Palmers</hi> words. Though yet you are pleaſed to call it, This Truth avouched by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119008:9"/> us, we meane, The ſickneſſe of our fancy, a Novell thing, never heard off in the world till now of late yeares, and had dyed in the veſſell, had not we broached-it, or ſet it a tap, as we may ſay in the place we live-in; To that purpoſe you ſpeake, and ſo <hi>Ironical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> if we can underſtand you.</p>
            <p>3. But, Sir, to let theſe ſcornes paſſe with contempt from us enough, if not with as much ſorrow from our hearts for you; Is it poſſible, That you a <hi>Maſter</hi> in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and a <hi>Steward in God's Houſe,</hi> ſhould be ſuch a ſtranger to this Thing, "<hi>The way of Chriſt with His people,</hi> followiug on in His ſteps? No more. Yet, Sir, we take leave to aske you, why would you put your ſelfe to all the coſt of time and Spirits in returning your Anſwer to ſuch a light and Frothy Tenet, which might be brooded upon ſome few yeares ſince, but hatched but a few months agoe? Had any of us been as youthfull, frolicke, and venturous as your ſonne is, twenty to one wee had written Blaſphemie anent thoſe very words: but bleſſed be God we are better taught, and have not ſo learned Chriſt.</p>
            <p>4. But indeed, Sir, however you may be informed, or wholy miſtaken in your information, your Anſwer was not deſired, therefore not expected. It was enquired onely whether Mr <hi>Owen</hi> (of whom we had heard, "<hi>hee is asking the way to Zion with his face thitherward;</hi> therefore wee enquired whether he) had any ſight or knowledge of our papers, or intimation about them. Onely ſo, which might argue us more carefull than wee now are or ſee cauſe to be about that matter. Yet be it knowne unto you, we would rather heare three words in Reference to our matters from him, or any other of thoſe fix we addreſſed our ſelves unto in our Epiſtle, (ſo be they be not of your perſwaſion) than three thouſand words from you. And we more than hinted our Reaſon wherefore in the ſame place; Therefore Sir, you might have ſaved your ſelfe that labour, had it pleaſed you, for we know full well, what manner of anſwer we ſhould have from you of the ſame perſwaſion with Mr <hi>H:</hi> and paceing or driveing together as friends in the ſame way. And Truely Sir, we thinke it a little ſtrange, that you could imagine, that we could put any account at all upon any anſwer from you, in the ſame way with him, ſo often mentioned, unleſſe you had ſome hope to bring us over to that way, which ſo many finde without ſeeking.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119008:9"/>
            <p>5. Wee applied our ſelves to thoſe worthy men, your good neighbours and friends, as we are informed, the manner of peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able men is to doe. But ſeeing it pleaſed them not, as you ſay, neither th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one nor th' other to meddle in theſe matters contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted betwixt us, leaſt, as the Proverb is, "<hi>They ſhould take a dog by the eares,</hi> being of the ſame minde, as may be conceived, as one was, who ſaid, "he alwayes hated two kinde of ſtudies, "<hi>Studium partium et "ſtudium novarum rerum;</hi> Now our matters are novell ſay you, for it was never heard of in the world ſince the world was till now adayes, (1) <hi>That all groſſely ignorant and ſtudiouſly wicked</hi> (the chiefe head of our controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) <hi>are not to be admitted to the Lord's Supper.</hi> That is a novell Tenet, an yeſter dayes fiction; ſo alſo is this, (2) "<hi>They that have received Chriſt muſt walke in Him, even as He walked, That a Goſpell light ſhould be adorned and beautified with a Goſpell life, a walke or converſation as becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt. (3) That the ſtewards in Gods Houſe, ſhould looke well to this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they admit to Goſpell Communions.</hi> (4) For that every man <hi>is guilty of all the evill, which he hath power, and a call to hinder;</hi> A beame from our new light all this, which made not the leaſt glimmering in our world, till of late, ſome months or few yeares agoe: You may pardon this digreſſion. We returne to that wee were ſaying, which was this, That ſith it pleaſed not thoſe much honoured men to meddle in theſe matters, we are well pleaſed, though, we made tender thereof unto them; and not diſpleaſed, much leſſe diſcouraged at all, That it is refuſed, for poſſibly the controverſie muſt not be taken-up in ſo ſilent a way.</p>
            <p>6. Beſides, which is our Confidence, and makes us humbly bold, we have a God in Chriſt to goe unto, who is our <hi>Prophet</hi> to ſpeake to us as well as our <hi>Prieſt</hi> to ſpeake for us; our <hi>Oracle</hi> as well as our <hi>Advocate,</hi> He will take us by <hi>the hand,</hi> and <hi>teach us how to goe,</hi> ſo long as by His grace with us, we beg nothing more earneſtly of Him, and finde it in our hearts to be as unwilling to tread one ſtep (wandring ſheep though we are) out of His way, as is a wearied traveller to goe out of his; And poſſible alſo we had not ſtood ſo faſt in Him, with our eye ſo fixed upon Him, and our-foote in His way, as now we doe, and through His grace ſhall doe (which loves to ſtrengthen His weakeſt ones, To mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119008:10"/> His owne power in them, and with them, when their's is <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>God loves to ſhew the world what His ſtrength can doe in a weak crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, as well as what His Grace and Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cy can doe for a ſinful creature. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Caryl on Job 6. 11. 475.</note> gone) had we not from our firſt <hi>footing, "the way of Holineſſe,</hi> and all along to this Day felt many ſhockes, and as many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, contumelies and reproaches caſt upon us, and the way, no man ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding by us the while, no not a man of Name for learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and pietie. And which is almoſt as bad, but God will make all good, and even this beſt of all, You that are a ſteward in God's houſe, and ſhould, like a good ſteward, take them into your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, whom your Lord and Maſter is pleaſed to take by the hand, that is, "<hi>To give ſpeciall helpe unto,</hi> you are ſo farre from doeing this, That you doe little leſſe than maintaine a war againſt them, (we meane all them all over the Land that deſine to walke with a <hi>right foote,</hi> according to Goſpel-order in Church-Society: For what are we, that we ſhould complaine in our own behalfe) which exceedingly gladdeth the hearts of the wicked, <hi>who 'love to have it ſo,</hi> and ſo their hand is ſtrengthened mightily, and their foote ſtabliſhed in their <hi>owne way</hi> of ſin and Death.</p>
            <p>But what though, and things ſtand thus? God is in the midſt of His people, He ſtands by them, and will ſtrengthen them, and in His owne time, beſt for His people, He will raiſe them, they ſhall not ſtill lie in the Duſt of Debaſement: His Jewells ſhall be made-up, which now lie as in the mire trod under-foote, which is permitted, and not barely ſo, and no more, for Gods permiſſion is a "<hi>providence,</hi> and that is "<hi>active,</hi> to drive His people out of themſelves, from putting any <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Self Depen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance looſeneth from God.</hi> D. Preſton.</note> 
               <hi>confidence in the fleſh,</hi> That <hi>their hope may be ſet on Him</hi> (which is ſetleing) Who raiſeth the dead; For commonly ſo it is, The more we have of the creature, the leſſe we have of God; becauſe the fuller ſight we have of the creature, the leſſe we looke after Him, not apprehending out needs of Him, who fills all, meaſuring-forth to all as pleaſeth Him, <hi>and is All in All.</hi> O that we did not caſt ſo much about us for a looke of favour from a man of high degree, and could more looke unto God for His favour, who lookes after His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>following them with His eye upon them,</hi> Pſal. 34. 15. that is "<hi>will deale well with them,</hi> Jer: 40. 4. and beſt of all at the laſt: Wee Truſt the Lord is every Day inſtructing us to this Diſcretion, ſo as we ſhall be daily leſſe in our ſelves, and more in God. And then "<hi>let the weake ſay, we are ſtrong.</hi> And they that are ſtrong
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119008:10"/> out of Him, O that they did know how weake they are; or if ſtrong their ſtrength will be their Confuſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>SECT. IV.</head>
            <p>SEcondly, There is another thing we would ſpeake unto a little, that we may give ſatisfaction to others, for you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive none from us, and we as little from you.</p>
            <p>You enjoyned us to give you an account of our way, why it is not the ſame with yours, which is the ſame with the man ſo often mentioned.</p>
            <p>This now we have done, according to the Talent, or two mites rather, the onely wiſe God hath entruſted us with, in <hi>all</hi> "<hi>Godly ſimplicity.</hi> And now you returne to us againe and againe; That we have ſaid very much, but little or nothing to purpoſe, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludingly. And That another might have ſaid much more and to more purpoſe in foure lines, than we have done in foure Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes; And ſo ſay wee too; for there is ſuch a naturall power in our hands, that we could have ſaid very little, and yet leſſe to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But yet Sir, we will not blame your little, nor ſhould you, we thinke, ſo much blame our much; Onely we take leave to tell you our Paſtors words (for though we doe not, yet you and he ſtand upon a levell, <hi>That he was young, and now is old,</hi> yet from his childhood to this very day, ſtill verſed amidſt papers all his dayes) he never ſaw ſo much thronged together in ſo little roomth, ſo little and ſo much; ſo little to the heart, he beleives of every truely godly man, ſo much to the heart of the wicked, who <hi>love to have it ſo,</hi> even as men of your way and perſwaſion would have it; Juſtifying Mr <hi>H:</hi> in every line, and reproaching the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the Lords anointed, we had almoſt ſaid, in every word, relating to that Controverſie. The one cannot be without th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he that doth th'one, doth both;—That's all wee were ordered to tell you, but from hence we will conclude in our owne behalfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is not the <hi>muchneſſe</hi> that diſpleaſeth, but that it is much againſt the graine of our ſpirits; And then be it little or much, it is all one, it much diſpleaſeth. But ſuppoſe that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119008:11"/> much, which is ſpoken, is much after the graine of our Spirits; why, though there be not a <hi>graine of Salt</hi> in it, Yet, how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is it! as wine and ſtrong drinke is to the pallate of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and as greedily taken-in as Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> Bookes are (to the heart of all the moſt vile and abominable in the Land) or as that graſſe is to ſheepe which rotts them. More and more of that, <hi>which is ſweete,</hi> ſaid <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> hearers, as hee tells us, more and yet more of that, though it <hi>"choake us;</hi> when a little of that, which is <hi>Croſſe-grained</hi> to us, as Truth is, doth not a little diſpleaſe us. It is not how much or how little, but how it goes with or againſt our Spirits, This renders it much or very little diſpleaſing. So we are concluded. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thus we would conclude alſo; That, though All you and we have ſpoken is but in words, yet we doubt not, and you may hope the ſame of us, Your Eare and Endeavour was to ſpeake more than words, elſe they are nothing but winde; And then, as one ſaith, He that hath ſpoken but one ſuch word, hath ſpoken too many by one. Yet</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In reference to a multitude of words charged upon us; we grant that, there may be <hi>plenty of words,</hi> but <hi>ſcarcitie of matter,</hi> and there may be plenty of matter in few words: Some have the skill of it to ſpeake much in a little, to contract, as it were, the <hi>Spirits of a point</hi> in to a few words, and ſo can give you much in a little a large matter in a narrow Compaſſe. But could wee skill of this thing, vvee vvould not ſhew it in our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, vvhich tend to informe them, that are as weake to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, as hard and ſlow to underſtand, as vvee our ſelves are, not able to apprehend that, which is couched and drawne-up ſo cloſe together; Much may be ſpoken to us in a little, but vvee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand but little in much: <hi>All are not able to "drinke Spirits;</hi> but <hi>must have them infuſed into, and incorporated with larger diſcourſes and perticular demonſtrations.</hi> We, as all they that are the ſame with us, "<hi>Babes in Chriſt,</hi> muſt have "<hi>line upon line, and precept upon precept,</hi> that is, a multitude of lines and precepts. In a word, Better The <hi>Grammarian ſhould blame us, than that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not underſtand us,</hi> was the old ſaying, and may plead our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as was hinted in our Epiſtle to you; vvhence it was That when you expected our Anſwer in ſeaven lines, we could not doe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119008:11"/> it in leſſe than ſeaven Treatiſes. And yet we expect not our matters ſhould finde acceptance for the muchneſſe or length thereof, nor yours perhaps, for the ſcantneſſe or ſhortneſſe of it; You and vvee muſt ſubſcribe to this Truth in Reference to our matters, <hi>Right perſwaſion proceedeth not ſo much from the Power of the ſpeaker, as from the diſpoſition of the hearer;</hi> if he be averſe from that he heares, or his eare be foreſtalled, ſpeake you much, or ſpeake you little, it's all one, you had as good ſpeake to a mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt, and bid it move and turne to you. And ſo much to that Objection.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>SECT. V.</head>
            <p>THere is a third thing you mention to us, wherein vve vvould give you what ſatisfaction vve can, before wee come to that wherewith vvee vvill conclude.</p>
            <p>3. Our Paſtour is invited by you to tell Mr <hi>Ford</hi> in a Letter to him, his exceptions againſt ſome paſſages in his booke <hi>for Infant Baptiſme,</hi> that he may cleare them in his next impreſſion, which vvee vviſh heartily he may doe, if poſſible to be don</p>
            <p>Sir, we will not gueſs at your Reaſon, why you deſire our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour to deale vvith your Brother by Letter; You know, Sir, he alwayes declined this Conteſt, nor could he be perſwaded to have medled in theſe matters, but that wee were queſtioned by your ſelfe about them. And ſo, he ſtanding in that Relation unto us, he could not doe leſſe than what he hath don, and doe his dutie; ſo then to proceed, You may remember how fully and clearely vvee dealt with your Brother and your ſelfe in this matter.</p>
            <p>Thus it was, to repeate things againe, ſo ſoone as our Paſtour eaſt his eye upon the 78, and ſo forward to th' 83 page of your brothers booke, he ſaw clearely, That the Tenets your brother holds-to there are the pillar and ground, <hi>"Free Admiſſion of all to all Church-Communions beareth upon:</hi> The very Tenour it holds-by; vvhereupon vve ſaw it clearely our dutie (for vvee vvere queſtioned about it, and not our Paſtour; ſo what he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took and hath don, it was upon the account of Truth, and for our ſakes) after we had done our worke, in order to your ſatisfaction, to returne unto it againe, and to make a diſtinct Worke or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119008:12"/> of it. And hereof we gave you and him intimation in our Epiſtle to you, and in that other to him, and his fellow-bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as alſo in our firſt Treatiſe, by an inſertion there. And all this, that we might doe as becommeth all things according to the Goſpell Rule, and right order; vvee made tender of our booke againe and againe, that hee might have the fight of it, for vvee vvould rather offend our ſelves, than him or your ſelfe, or any good man. But upon what account, he and you beſt know, it was refuſed; And ſo after two moneths expectation, and then a flat deniall, together with ſomewhat more you wott off; We ceaſed, as in point of good manners, it was fit for us to doe; for vvhat could we ſay or doe more? Indeed we know not; we ſaw our papers that were ſent, returned with contempt and more, (They might fare the worſe for their Authour, For the <hi>counſell is ſeldome loved, if the Counſeller be not,</hi> though yet Truth is lovely, what ever the Speaker bee) The other three vvee prepared, we offered and yee refuſed them; We ſay againe, vvhat could we doe more? and being fully reſolved, we have done full-up to our duty; our Paſtour willed us to tell you farther, That whereas he purpoſed his ſaid bookes, and that ſaid Treatiſe (the ſixt in order) ſhould ſee the light not before the Authour thereof be carried to the place of Darkneſſe, That then his bookes may ſpeake <hi>for the way of Truth, fellow-walkers therein,</hi> and <hi>helpers of the ſame,</hi> ſo mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly oppoſed now adayes; and for the vindication of that, he <note place="margin">We are taught to vindicate our Credit, when the Truth is wounded through the ſides thereof.</note> accounts better than riches, when his body muſt be laid in the place of Silence; For why may it not be hoped, at leaſt, why not endeavoured, That when his body is laid to ſleep in the Duſt of Death, his Name may riſe from the Duſt of Debaſement? how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the will of the Lord be done.</p>
            <p>But ſo he intended and fully purpoſed in his heart then, and not till then to ſend that and other Treatiſes abroad into the world. But obſerving ſome ſignall providence, This (1) That Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> pleadings for <hi>free Admiſſion</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be ſo pleaded for by a Miniſter of the Goſpell, and Steward in His houſe, a leading man and a Carrying man with the moſt of the profeſſors in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he lives-in; And this after foure Worthies of the Lord have ſtood up in the might of God againſt him, ſpeaking ſo much and ſo clearely from the Holy Scriptures to that point of <hi>non-admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119008:12"/> of all,</hi> that it had been enough <hi>to ſtop the mouth of the Devill</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Preface to B. <hi>Cat: p.</hi> 68.</note> 
               <hi>himſelfe,</hi> which one ſaid of an eminently learned and godly man aſſerting the Truth againſt gain-ſayers. (2) And nextly to ſay the leaſt, and as little as can be, "<hi>The defaming of many</hi> Miniſters and people round about him. (3) And which pinches and preſſes yet more, if more can be, your pointing us to your Son's handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke in his Treatiſe of Prayer, ſpecially the Lords Prayer, where he chargeth the Rev: Authour with Blaſphemy upon Blaſphemy, here one and there another, and there a third; for this and that, and the other: But (4) ſpecially for <hi>Truths-ſake,</hi> and the way of Holineſſe, which, as is conceived, ſuffers much herein, through the ſpewings, you have given too juſt an occaſion to be caſt thereupon, he will endeavour his utmoſt to give all, that will, a ſight of all that is written, making this Aſſuance withall to his Reader; Firſt, That how evilly-ſoever he is ſpoken off and dealt withall, yet he can doe nothing againſt the Truth, but in deſire and endeavour, all, he poſſibly can, for it, the promoting of the ſame in the hearts and lives of Gods people. And (2) That they, who are helpers together with him of That Bleſſed thing, ſhall be helped by him to the utmoſt of thoſe abilities his Lord and heavenly Father is pleaſed to Communicate to him. And he is perſwaded, That This God <hi>Whom he hath Truſted</hi> will, as He hath done hitherto, ſo to th' end, help both him and them; And in the laſt place, This he added more, That rather than he would, in the leaſt greive the Leaſt of the Lords little ones knowingly, he would his tongue ſhould cleave to the roof of his mouth rather, and his pen to his Fingers ends; That his hand ſhould fall off from his arme, and his arme from his ſhoulder-blade. We come now to the fourth and laſt, and Then we have done.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VI.</head>
            <p>4. SO we give you, Sir, to know, That our Paſtour with our ſelves have taken full notice, as you willed us, of your Sons handy-worke, in the Margent of that Treatiſe our Paſtour hath written about <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and in ſpeciall the "<hi>Lords-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> whereof you were more than an occaſion, or <hi>cauſa ſine quâ non;</hi> we have as we were ſayiug well obſerved your Sons Charge
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119008:13"/> of blaſphemy there. And Truely had it not been your Son, whom we have knowne ſo well, we had wondred at it. Beſides he is but young, a youth-full Man; Yet theſe words may fit very well; An evill time ſure, ſad things are comming, "<hi>The Child ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelfe proudly againſt the Auncient;</hi> and, which aggravates the fault, we thinke, the Son ſhall doe this, the Father ſtanding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and giving allowance to it, and which might, in ſome mens thoughts, highten it to a Crime, the father of the Childe a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpell, allowing his Son ſo dealing with his fellow-Miniſter, and little leſſe than boaſting of it, if not glorying in it, when it was ſo done. Your owne acknowledgement, Sir, Mr <hi>Ford</hi> and Mr <hi>Owen</hi> with your ſelfe were at your Sons Elbow, at leaſt he was within the ſound of your words, which were theſe, "<hi>Take heed, Son, what you write, that it be no more than what you can Anſwer, "I'le warrant you for that, ſaid he:</hi> Say we; ſhould you have taken his warrant, being ſo youthfull a Man and knowne ſo to be? Say you, for we make bold to queſtion you about this matter, though were vve as much above you in place, as vve are below you, we would not be ſo bold with you, as you know who was, vvhen the Childe offended in the preſence of the Father, he excuſed the Son <hi>à tanto</hi> if not <hi>à toto,</hi> and laid all the blame upon the Father, and gave him a box on the eare, withall ſuffering the Childe to doe a thing ſo unbecomming in the preſence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So we returne to you, and This onely we would ſay, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire we pray you at your Oracle (we meane not your ſelfe, for if we counted you an Oracle, as, you ſay, we did, we ſee, we were miſ-taken; Yet becauſe we think vvee did not, vve vvill not aske pardon) vve pray you enquire of Gods Word, That Oracle, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you, being the father of the Childe, ſhould not have ſeene what the Childe had written? Suppoſing you had ſo done; It will be ſuppoſed alſo, we thinke, that for "<hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> you would have Commanded him to have written "<hi>Errour;</hi> Yet that would have been too heavie a Charge too, upon theſe words, againſt which blaſphemy ſtands charged, "<hi>That the Lords-prayer is a dead letter,</hi> for had there been a Spirit of life and quickning in thoſe words, commonly ſaid with the ſpeed of a good Clarke by Miniſters of your perſwaſion, way, and judgement, what a growne and Tall-man in Chriſt had your Son been by this time of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119008:13"/> Day, being taught this prayer in his Cradle, by your owne Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, uſing it upward all along, and at this very day ſaying it now very Clarke-like in the Pulpit; ſo tenaciouſly he holds to that, the manner of us all, he had learn't in his Cradle. And True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sir, others may think you your ſelfe had made clearer Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the good Spirit ſpeaking in you, had the words of that prayer been Spirit and life unto you, having ſaid it ſo often in our hearing at th' end of your owne; Well, Sir, but if this be ſo as your Son ſaith, "The Lords prayer is a <hi>quick'ning letter,</hi> and he that ſaith contrary "<hi>blaſphemeth,</hi> then you doe well, and your bounden dutie (as we Country-folke ſay) teaching it your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; yet our perſwaſion is from the premiſes, ſo from this alſo, which followes, That it cannot be as your Son ſaith, That this ſaid prayer, ſhould be Spirit and life, while yet the moſt vile and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons in the world ſay it every day, for few ſay any other, and moſt ſolemnely on the Lords day after you, when you ſay it. We commend your Son to your care and good counſell, he ſtands in great need of it: And we pray for you, That you may ſtand in Gods Counſell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VII.</head>
            <p>BUt theſe two things we are Commanded to tell you, and ſo an end of this matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That had an elder and wiſer man than your Son charged <note place="margin">Ab ineunt aetate ſuâ luſil in art? dialecticâ nunc in ſacris ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inſanit.</note> our book in that manner, it would have reminded our Paſtour of one he hath read of ſome where, <hi>who, when he was young made himſelfe merry with his Sophiſtrie, and afterwards when he waxed old ſhewed himſelfe mad in Divinity,</hi> and ſo ſported with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture alſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That you never ſtirred the Coales till now; yet doe we not now, much leſſe have we ſo done, ſhew the leaſt heat, which you call fire againſt you, or your Son, whether our bowells are not ſtirred with compaſſion over you both, the Lord knowes. Though yet againſt thoſe blacke and horrid doings in God's houſe, we have declaimed with zeale not enough, yet, we hope, that which was, was according to knowledge: So alſo againſt the Obſervation of the Day commonly called <hi>Chriſtmas-day:</hi> Againſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119008:14"/> this and th' other, ſince you have raiſed us like an huge Bell, we will make the Sound thereof, our cry againſt it, and <hi>free admiſſion of all,</hi> goe forth through the whole Land, as the Sound of Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> Bookes have done; wee will doe our Endeavour, and the Lord God <hi>doe what is good in His owne eyes;</hi> for if this may prove a <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable opinion</hi> in the iſſue; That <hi>all are to be admitted to the Lords Table,</hi> how <hi>notorious ſoever for their deboyſery.</hi> And this alſo, That <hi>the Day ſhould be kept holy,</hi> which <hi>hath not the Lords Sanction upon it,</hi> Then we ſee not but that there may be <hi>a damnable ſilence</hi> (which is the thing in queſtion betwixt your ſelfe and us, and will fall into conſideration in its reſpective place) in thoſe who ſhould oppoſe them. <hi>Every one muſt give account of his idle words;</hi> and <hi>a Miniſter for his idle ſilence,</hi> ſaith that worthy man Mr <hi>W: Jinken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have given our perſwaſion alſo touching <hi>formes of prayer,</hi> and in ſpeciall reſolved ſome Queries about the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> not ſo much as blameing, much leſſe Cenſuring or judgeing them, that uſe formes, or that forme of prayer at the end of their's. Wee have given the reaſons of our perſwaſion, why we thinke it not ſo comely; When wee have your Reaſons for your doeings in that and other matters, which we will not be ſo bold, as you might be with our Paſtour, ſo much as to entreate of you, poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly we may be of your minde in theſe things, but we thinke it no eaſie worke for you to give us any thing that hath the <hi>ſhape of Reaſon,</hi> thereby to make ſuch proofe of your doeings in Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to thoſe matters under-hand, that they are ordered accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the mind and will of your God.</p>
            <p>We will conclude with a few words to thoſe Miniſters that ſenſe with Mr <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and walke together with him in his way in point of Church-Adminiſtrations; (1) That ſome witts will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to make a <hi>faire cover,</hi> even of the very ſacred Scriptures, for the moſt deformed and groſſeſt errours among which we doe reckon this, relating to free admiſſion of all to all Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions. (2) And that a ſad account will be given of that time, and of thoſe parts, which have been laid-out in the patronage of ſuch matters, that lie cleane Croſſe to the graine of Truth. For it is as ſinfull (to uſe that learned mans words upon <hi>Job)</hi> to ſew <note place="margin">Job. 11. 530.</note> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">fig-leaves, or make faire pretexts to cover the nakednes of our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119008:14"/> opinion, as of our practiſes, Therefore he that can receive it, let him receive it. <hi rend="italic">Prov:</hi> 30. 32. <hi rend="italic">If thou haſt done evill in liſting-up thy ſelfe, or if thou haſt thought evill</hi> (or maintained evill) <hi rend="italic">lay thy hand upon thy mouth:</hi>
               </hi> Speake no more, never be an Advocate in a bad cauſe, though it be thine owne. When our errours are ſhewne us (as theſe have been in Reference to free Admiſſion by foure, as was ſaid one after another, we ſhould not open our mouths, unleſſe it be to renounce and diſclaime them—But we have done.</p>
            <p>And that we may be ſtill doing, and be ſure to doe our duty, let us pray each for other; "<hi>The Lord deliver us from Evill:</hi> The guidance of our owne Spirits, as bad and worſe to us, than is that of the world: And give us a ſound minde, whether the body be ſound, or unſound, no great matter, The ſound mind is all, the Mind that was in Chriſt, and is in all ſound Chriſtians. And this labour of Love and worke of Faith is but full-up to that lovely rule, "<hi>Whom we Reprove openly, we ſhould pray for ſecretly.</hi> 
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
